Thompson Family papers, 1834-1864 (bulk 1861-1864)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Thompson Family papers, 1834-1864 (bulk 1861-1864)
MS 266
Thompson family
The collection consists mainly of letters, 1861-1864, from James Thompson to his wife Charlotte Thompson. These are firsthand accounts of army life and Civil War battles, and are written from Illinois, Tennessee, and Mississippi.
.2 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Bowman Thompson, 1811-1865, was born in Northumberland County, England. He immigrated to the United States about 1830 and subsequently settled on a farm in Summit County, Ohio. In 1834, he married Elizabeth Cannon, daughter of John and Elizabeth (Gilchrist) Cannon. They had five sons and two daughters.
Two of the sons, Robert and James, fought for the Union during the Civil War. Robert Thompson, -1861, served in Company G of the 37th Illinois Regiment Infantry, commonly known as "Fremont's Rifles," and was involved in Fremont's attempt to subdue a small militant force in southwest Missouri. On December 5, 1861, Rober was reported missing.
James Thompson, 1840-1912, was born in Summit County, Ohio where he received a common-school education. He married Charlotte S. Oliver on January 1, 1861 before enlisting with Company L, 4th Illinois Volunteer Cavalry unit on January 13. During the Civil War, James served at Corrinth, Massachusetts, and also was with his regiment during the battle of Coffeeville. After completing his term of enlistment, he was mustered out in October 1864, having attained the rank of Commissary Sergeant. He resumed his occupation as a farmer. In subsequent years, he also held the posts of Collector, Supervisor and Postmaster. He moved to Grenola, Kansas in 1905.
Organization
This collection is organized into four series.
Series I: Biography and Genealogy
Series II: Correspondence, 1851-1864
Series III: Legal Documents, 1834-1856
Series IV: Sketches
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists mainly of letters, 1861-1864, from James Thompson to his wife Charlotte Thompson. These are firsthand accounts of army life and Civil War battles, and are written from Illinois, Tennessee, and Mississippi. Other letters include some written to Bowman and Elizabeth Thompson, from son, Robert; most are from Missouri before he died there in 1861. Earlier correspondence, 1851-1858, contains letters to Bowman from his sister, Jane Thompson Bland, in England. Bowman's copies of the English wills of his parents and siblings are present, dating from 1840-1856. Two original drawings depict Lowther Castle, the Thompson family castle in England, and Askham Church, Westmoreland County, England. An 1834 Ohio deed is also present.
Access Terms
Thompson, Robert, d. 1861 -- Correspondence
Thompson, James, 1840-1912 -- Correspondence
Bland, Jane Thompson -- Correspondence
Thompson, Bowman, 1811-1865
Thompson family -- Genealogy
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives
Correspondence
Drawings
Wills
Container List
- Series I: Biography and Genealogy
  - Biography and Genealogy. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1851-1864
  - Letters of Jane Thompson Bland, Westmoreland County, England to Summit County, Ohio. (Six letters) 1851-1858 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters of Robert Thompson to his parents, Bowman and Elizabeth (Cannon) Thompson. (Seven letters) August 30, 1861 to March 5, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes letters sent from:
    Camp Webb, Chicago, Illinois
    Benton Barracks, St. Louis, Missouri
    Boonsville, Missouri
    Otterville, Missouri
    Syracuse, Missouri
  - Letters of James Thompson to his wife Charlotte Thompson. (132 letters) 1861 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Camp James, Mound City, Illinois
    Camp Hunter, Ottawa, Illinois
    Camp Wallace
    Camp Bowman
    Camp Davis, Springfield, Illinois
    Camp Cairo, Cairo, Illinois
  - Letters of James Thompson to his wife Charlotte Thompson. (1 of 2) (132 letters) 1862 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Fort Henry, Tennessee
    Fort Donelson, Tennessee
    Camp Tumuli
    Pittsburg Landing
    Camp No. 10 near Corrinth, Mississippi
    Camp near Chivalla
    Moscow, Tennessee
    Memphis, Tennessee
    Trenton, Tennessee
    Humbolt, Tennessee
    Oxford, Tennessee
    Watervalley, Mississippi
  - Letters of James Thompson to his wife Charlotte Thompson. (2 of 2) (132 letters) 1862 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters of James Thompson to his wife Charlotte Thompson. (132 letters) 1863 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    La Grange, Tennessee
    Bolivar, Tennessee
    Natchez, Tennessee
    Jackson, Tennessee
    Fort Pickering, Memphis, Tennessee
    Collierville, Tennessee
    Vicksburg, Mississippi
    Natchez, Mississippi
  - Letters of James Thompson to his wife Charlotte Thompson. (132 letters) 1864 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Camp Butler, Springfield, Illinois
- Series III: Legal Documents, 1834-1856
  - Wills of John, Sara and John Thompson, Deed to John Campbell of Wayne County, Ohio. 1834, 1840-1856 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Will of Hannah Thompson, John Thompson 1842-1951 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series IV: Sketches
  - Ink sketch of Askham Church, Westmoreland County, England. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ink sketch of Lowther Castle, the Thompson family castle, England. (exact location unknown) (Box 1, Folder 11)